# Alexander Kirchner-Häusler

Address: Flat 10 Hilltop House, Glen Iris Avenue, Canterbury, Kent, CT2 8HP

Email: a.kirchner[at]kent.ac.uk | Telephone: +44 (0)1227 816587

Twitter | LinkedIn | UoKent

### PERSONAL STATEMENT

Post-doctoral researcher in Cultural Psychology at the University of Kent, and affiliate researcher at the Center for Social and Cultural Psychology at the KU Leuven. My work explores the many dynamic ways culture is reproduced in our relationships and interactions with others around us, and particularly focuses on the important role of emotions in supporting cultural systems of being and relating (e.g. cultures of honor).

### **EMPLOYMENT HISTORY**

10/2019 – 10/2024	Post-doctoral Researcher   University of Kent, Canterbury, UK Project "The Cultural Logic of Honor and Social Interaction: A Cross-Cultural Comparison" (Supervised by Prof. Ayse Uskul) <a href="https://www.honorlogic.org">https://www.honorlogic.org</a>
05/2019 – 01/2020	Post-doctoral Researcher   KU Leuven, Center for Social and Cultural Psychology, Leuven, Belgium Project "Conflict in Mother-Daughter Dyads from Belgium and Japan" (Supervised by Prof. Batja Mesquita and Assistant Professor Dr. Koen Luyckx)
12/2014 – 05/2019	PhD Researcher   KU Leuven, Center for Social and Cultural Psychology, Leuven, Belgium Supervised by Prof. Batja Mesquita, Prof. Peter Kuppens and Dr. Michael Boiger
10/2009 – 02/2012	<b>Student Research Assistant</b>   Department of Social Psychology, Goethe-University, Frankfurt am Main, Germany Supervised by Prof. Rolf van Dick
06/2009 – 11/2009	<b>Student Research Assistant  </b> Department of Evaluation & QA, Johann-Wolfgang-von-Goethe-University, Frankfurt am Main, Germany Supervised by Prof. Karl Schweizer

## **EDUCATION / ACADEMIC HISTORY**

12/2014 – 05/2019	PhD in Cultural Psychology   KU Leuven, Center for Social and Cultural Psychology, Leuven, Belgium Research Project: "Cultural Differences in Emotions: The Role of Interpersonal Systems" Supervised by Prof. Batja Mesquita, Prof. Peter Kuppens and Dr. Michael Boiger
10/2013 – 10/2014	MSc in Applied Social Psychology   University of Sussex, Brighton, UK Graduated with distinction Master Thesis Topic: "The effect of hate crime on self-attributed humanness" Supervised by Prof. Rupert Brown
08/2010 - 01/2011	BSc in Psychology   The College of New Jersey, Ewing, NJ, USA Undergraduate Exchange Stay
10/2008 – 10/2012	BSc in Psychology   Goethe-University, Frankfurt am Main, Germany  Bachelor Thesis Topic: "Transformational and Transactional Leadership in the CLBO – Interviews: An Explorative Study"

Supervised by Prof. Rolf van Dick

08/2005 - 04/2008 Abitur (A-Levels) | Albert-Einstein-School, Schwalbach am Taunus, Germany

Major Subjects German and Mathematics

08/1999 – 06/2005 Heinrich-von-Kleist Middle School, Eschborn, Germany

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

- **Kirchner-Häusler, A.**, Boiger, M., Uchida, Y., Higuchi, A., Uchida, Y., & Mesquita, M. (2020). "Relatively Happy": ratios of positive & negative affect and relationship satisfaction in two cultural contexts. Manuscript submitted to the Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology.
- Boiger, M., **Kirchner-Häusler, A.**, Schouten, A., Uchida, Y., & Mesquita, M. (2020). *Different Bumps in the Road: The Emotional Dynamics of Couple Disagreements in Belgium and Japan*. Manuscript submitted to Emotion.
- Schouten, A., Boiger, M., **Kirchner-Häusler, A.**, Uchida, Y., & Mesquita, B. (2020). Cultural Differences in Emotion Suppression in Belgian and Japanese Couples: A Social Functional Model. *Frontiers in Psychology*, *11*, 1048. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2020.01048">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2020.01048</a>
- **Kirchner, A.**, Boiger, M., Uchida, Y., Norasakkunkit, V., Verduyn, P., & Mesquita, B. (2018). Humiliated fury is not universal: the co-occurrence of anger and shame in the United States and Japan. *Cognition and Emotion*, 32(6), 1317-1328. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/02699931.2017.1414686">https://doi.org/10.1080/02699931.2017.1414686</a>
- Braun, S., Bark, A. H., **Kirchner, A.**, Stegmann, S., & van Dick, R. (2015). Emails From the Boss—Curse or Blessing? Relations Between Communication Channels, Leader Evaluation, and Employees' Attitudes. *International Journal of Business Communication*, 56(1), 50-81. https://doi.org/10.1177%2F2329488415597516
- **Kirchner-Häusler, A.**, Boiger, M., Ozcanli, F., Uchida, Y., & Mesquita, M. (2019). Different Bumps to Adulthood: Emotion Dynamics in Belgian and Japanese Mother-Daughter Interactions. *Manuscript in preparation.*
- **Kirchner-Häusler, A.,** Boiger, M., Uchida, Y., & Mesquita, M. (2019). We move, We Stay, Together: Interpersonal patterns of affect in Belgium and Japan. *Manuscript in preparation.*

### **CONFERENCE SUBMISSIONS AND TALKS**

**04/2018** Presentation | 2018 Consortium for Emotion Research in Europe (CERE) in Glasgow,

Scotland, UK

Title: "We move, we stay, together: Interpersonal patterns of affect in Belgium and

Japan"

07/2017 Poster Presentation | 2017 EASP conference in Granada, Spain

Title: "Cultural Differences in self-reported affect and relationship satisfaction during

couple conflicts"

**07/2017** Presentation | Pre-conference meeting "Relationships and Health" at the 2017 EASP

conference in Granada, Spain

Title: "The role of positive affect for partner's satisfaction and wellbeing in two cultures"

07/2016 - 08/2016 Poster Presentation | 23rd Congress of the International Association for Cross-

Cultural Psychology, Nagoya, Japan

Title: "Conflict in Couples: Behavioral strategies and their relationship outcomes in the

US, Belgium and Japan"

**07/2015 Conference Talk |** Congress of the International Society for Research on Emotions,

Geneva, Switzerland

Title: "Humiliated Fury is not universal: The co-occurrence of anger and shame in the

U.S. and Japan"

03/2015 Poster Presentation | International Convention of Psychological Science, Amsterdam,

The Netherlands

Title: "The effect of hate crime on self-attributed humanness"

#### **TEACHING ACTIVITIES**

10/2016 - 05/2019 Teaching Assistant | Course: "Topics in Social and Cultural Psychology"

Supervised by Prof. Batja Mesquita & Dr. Michael Boiger

**04/2017 Teaching Assistant | Course:** "Masterproefonderwerp" (Master Thesis)

Writing Course for Master Theses at the KU Leuven

04/2010 - 02/2012 Teaching Assistant | "Experimental psychologisches Praktikum" (Lab Course for

**Undergraduate Students**)

Department of Social Psychology, Johann-Wolfgang-von-Goethe-University, Frankfurt

am Main, Germany

Supervised by Prof. Rolf van Dick & Associate Professor Dr. Johannes Ullrich

#### **SUPERVISION**

11/2019 - ongoing BSc Supervision | Rhea Bandini

**10/2017 – 10/2018 MSc Supervision |** Cato Hooyberghs

**10/2017 – 10/2018 MSc Supervision | Cara Smet** 

10/2017 – 10/2018 MSc Supervision | Iris Dresselaerts

**10/2014 – 10/2016 MSc Supervision** | Klara van Hoeck

10/2014 - 10/2016 MSc Supervision | Shakira Ronsmans

### OTHER PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

**12/2014 – 09/2018** Lab Manager | Center for Social and Cultural Psychology, KU Leuven, Leuven,

Belgium

10/2015 Organizer | Workshop "Scientific Writing"

Given by Prof. Robert Kail

Leuven, Belgium

02/2013 - 07/2013 Voluntary Research Work | Department of Social Psychology, Johann-Wolfgang-von-

Goethe-University, Frankfurt am Main, Germany

Resulted in Journal article: "Emails From the Boss—Curse or Blessing? Relations Between Communication Channels, Leader Evaluation, and Employees' Attitudes"

**04/2010 – 02/2012 Organizational Support** | Center for Leadership and Behavior in Organizations

(CLBO), Johann-Wolfgang-von-Goethe-University, Frankfurt am Main, Germany

#### INTERNSHIPS AND PRACTICAL TRAINING

04/2014 - 05/2014 Research Internship | Sussex University, Brighton, United Kingdom

Associated Project: "The experience of hate crime in minority communities"

Supervised by Dr. Jenny Paterson and Prof. Rupert Brown

02/2012 - 05/2012 Practical Internship | SHL Germany, Frankfurt am Main, Germany

Assessment Center and Recruitment

Supervised by Dipl.-Psych. Alexander Ratzel

07/2011 - 02/2012 Research Internship | Department of Educational Psychology, Goethe-University,

Frankfurt am Main, Germany

Associated Project "Measuring Physiological Correlates of Flow in Chess Players"

Supervised by Dipl.-Psych. Tahmine Tozman

**01/2011 – 04/2011** Research Internship | Intergroup Relations Laboratory, University of Delaware,

Newark, DE, USA

Supervised by Prof. Samuel Gaertner

#### ATTENDED WORKSHOPS AND COURSES

09/2020 Workshop "Multilevel Modeling using R"

Taught by Dr. Ella Roelant & Prof. Dr. Erik Fransen

Online Workshop by the Flanders' Training Network for Methodology and Statistics

07/2020 Workshop "Multilevel Modeling – A Second Course"

Taught byProf. Kristopher Preacher

Online Workshop offered by Statistical Horizons

01/2020 Workshop "UKRN Reproducibility Workshop 2020"

Organised by the UK Reproducibility Network

Cumberland Lodge, Windsor, UK

10/2018 Workshop "Introduction to Categorical Data Analysis with R"

Taught by Dr. Koen Plevoets

Workshop by the Flanders' Training Network for Methodology and Statistics

Hasselt, Belgium

10/2016 KU Leuven Seminar "Advanced Time Series Analysis"

Taught by Prof. Dr. Christophe Croux

Leuven, Belgium

06/2016 Workshop "Essential Tools for R"

Taught by Dr. Koen Plevoets

Workshop by the Flanders' Training Network for Methodology and Statistics

Leuven, Belgium

05/2016 KU Leuven Workshop "Supervising and Leading a Research Team"

Taught by Mieke van den Bossche

Leuven, Belgium

04/2015 Workshop "Facial Action Coding System"

Taught by Dr. Erika Rosenberg Amsterdam, The Netherlands

03/2015 Workshop "Longitudinal Data Analysis with MPLUS"

Workshop by the Flanders' Training Network for Methodology and Statistics Leuven, Belgium

10/2015 Workshop "Scientific Writing for Psychologists"

Taught by Prof. Robert Kail

Leuven, Belgium

### **SKILLS**

Software:

High Proficiency R, RMarkdown, Qualtrics, ILOG 4, SPSS, GSEQ4, Microsoft Office

Medium Proficiency R Shiny, MBCA, Limesurvey

**Basic Proficiency** GridWare, Surveymonkey, FaceReader, MPLUS

- Study Design and Management: rich experience with coordinating data collection in diverse cultural
  contexts, and setting up experimental and non-experimental study designs with uncommon population
  types (e.g. romantic couples, minority members)
- Statistical Modeling: Longitudinal models (Sequential Analysis, Growth Models), Dyadic Data Analysis (Interdependence Models, State Space Grids), Multilevel Modeling, Multi-Block Component Analysis

Canterbury, 01/07/2020

- Alexander Kirchner-Häusler -